<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jesuite discovered, or, A brief discourse of the policies of the Church of Rome, in preserving it self, and dividing of Protestant states and kingdomes in which, is plainly demonstrated, the effects of their political operations upon us at this day, in respect to religion, and matters of state.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S69</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11904475</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11904475</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 509:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jesuite discovered, or, A brief discourse of the policies of the Church of Rome, in preserving it self, and dividing of Protestant states and kingdomes in which, is plainly demonstrated, the effects of their political operations upon us at this day, in respect to religion, and matters of state.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: J.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50653:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JESUITE DISCOVERED; <hi>Or,</hi> A Brief DISCOURSE OF The Policies of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in Preſerving it Self, and Dividing of Proteſtant States and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>In which, is plainly Demonſtrated, the Effects of their Political operations upon Us at this Day, in reſpect to Religion, and matters of State.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gal. 3.1.</bibl>
               <p>O fooliſh <hi>Galatians,</hi> Who hath bewitched you, that you ſhould not Obey the Truth!</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50653:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50653:2"/>
            <head>TO The Reader.</head>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe of the <hi>Jeſuit Diſcovered,</hi> I intended that it ſhould have bin much larger and better Methodized; but that I, finding the Malevolent Influences of the Jeſuit, and the Common Enemy powred out ſo faſt upon Us, therefore Publiſhed it thus Rude and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndigeſted. This will not prevent the Evil, but it demonſtrateth that ſome courſe ought to be taken, that this Nation may come to a Conſiſtence in Government, elſe nothing but ruine will follow. So many Perſwaſions as we find in the Nation, ſo many Intereſts of State we may find alſo: unleſs all be wound up upon one bottom it will be a hard matter to ſave it from Deſtruction. The Saints Intereſt muſt not be onely conſulted, but alſo their Intereſt that are not accounted Saints; Our Saviour adviſeth his Apoſtles to let the Tares and the Wheat, grow together untill the Harveſt: Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is not attained unto in this Life, therefore our perſwaſion in Religion ought not, in point of its own ſafety, ſeek Predomination over another; It is to be bewayled amongst us, that mens merit by many is meaſured by their opinions. Tis true that the Jeſuit hath had more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for to practiſe upon us this laſt <hi>22</hi> years, than he had in <hi>100</hi> years before; and would do much more if he could perſwade you to take down, and throw in the duſt the Miniſters of Gods most holy Word. What think you of thoſe that ſay, They are dumb Doggs, Hirelings, and Antichriſtian? Did not the Jeſuit teach them to ſpell that Leſſon; Be ſober, Engliſhmen be ſober; you are Ridd by the Jeſuit, throw him off; ſeek after wholeſome Principles, that may be as Charts to ſayl by, in this Turbulent, Dangerous Sea, where you find nothing but Rocks and Shelves: He hath raiſed miſts that you cannot deſcry, nor
<pb facs="tcp:50653:3"/>make any true obſervation of your Land marks, that ſhould guide you into ſafe Harbor; He feedeth you with Notions that are ſweet in the mouth, but bitter in the belly, yea Poyſon; He infatuateth your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, that you cannot diſtinguiſh between Life and Death; He layeth his Snares at diſtances, and biddeth you walk as in a moſt pleaſant path; but (behold) you are taken in his Toyl: Do not look ſo a ſquint upon Him, who is not of your perſwaſion, but take him unto thee, and imbrace him, and ſay unto him, Brother, The Jeſuit hath endeavoured to ſet us at Odds. We are the ſame in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, Why ſhould thoſe ſmall Circumſtances be ſuch marks of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction and difference? Come, let us unite, and joyn hand in hand in the Work of our God and theſe Nations, that the People of the Lord in other Nations that ſhall hear of it may rejoyce, and his Enemies may fear and tremble, for that <hi>England</hi> is become an intire Piece, in the Building of the moſt Holy One.</p>
            <p>Unite, that you may not be broken. How much is the love of Gods People one towards another abated, ſince they were ſeparated by thoſe various distinctions amongſt us: If there were no more in it, but that of the preſerving love among thoſe that fear the Lord, it ſhould be a ſufficient Inducement to unite, and a prevayling perſwaſion to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt to it, as an Eſſential Dùty; but there is more alſo in it, <hi>viz.</hi> If you do not unite, your ruine will follow, and you will be broken one againſt another: What if one perſwaſion were fully poſſeſt with Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power, could they hold it? No: For that there is no one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion but muſt Exclude and Sever from their Intereſt ſix times their own number? Will Councel or Arms defend you in ſuch a Caſe? No, there is nothing Will or Can Defend or Preſerve, but union of all Intereſts, for which he prayeth, who is an unfained lover of the Church and People of God, and his Native Country,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have here briefly unlockt the Cabinet of the Policies of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and do deſire that others more able then my ſelf will make it their Work, to ſearch further in the myſteries of their Policies, that the evil intended by them to us may be thereby prevented. I alſo intend to do more of this matter, God Willing.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50653:3"/>
            <head>THE Jeſuit Diſcovered.</head>
            <p>THe policy of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> conſiſteth principally in dividing it Self into Divers and Sundry Orders, which are provided to retain all Humors in Mankind. By this, She preſerveth Her ſelf, and maketh Her Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtrong and powerful: and preſerveth Her ſelf from ruine, without which, She could not have continued to this Day, or bin able to act any thing to the hurt or detriment of the reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to the diverſity of Orders amongſt them; their onely policy to thoſe who deſpiſe the Wealth of the World, and that can content themſelves with Poverty, are the Mendicants; their Prelates abound in Riches, their Hermits and Capuchins for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of Life, their Cardinals for Pomp and Glory, their Jeſuits for Learning, and all manner of Sciences; their Popes and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates exerciſing Soveraignty and Princely Command: They take eſpecial care to ingage &amp; raviſh all manner of Humors. On the one ſide of a Street, you ſhall have a Nunnery, or Cloiſter of Virgins; on the other ſide a Sty of Courtizans. One Day you ſhall have them all in Masks, with all manner of Obſceneneſs and Folly that can be imagined, or the corrupt nature of man deſire; the Day following they will be all in Proceſſions, whipping themſelves until the blood cometh. On one Door you ſhall have Excommunications, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls and Bodyes to Hell: on another Door, a Jubilee; or full Diſcharge of all Villanies, Murthers, Fornication, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Forſwearing, Poyſoning; in a word, all manner of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50653:4"/>Sin, Lendneſs, and Impiety: They were led to this policy by the hand of Confeſſions; by that means they come to diſcern the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Mankind in general. They do not hold it ſafe to reſtrain any of theſe Humors, leſt it ſhould cauſe Eruptions, and make their Subjects ſeek ſome other way for to vent them in; ſo that theſe Orders are as Sinks to receive the Humors. They have not the Sword of the Spirit to deſtroy Vice, nor the Word of Truth to convince of evil Doing; therefore they muſt truſt to carnall Policy: <hi>For the more growth ſin hath among them, that more the Church Increaſeth in Riches,</hi> for that all puniſhment upon the matter, and pardons, are <hi>Pecuniary.</hi> The wayes they have to raviſh all ſorts of affections, as I ſayd before, are well-nigh infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, there being not any thing either Sacred or Prophane, no Vertue or Vice almoſt, nothing of how contrary condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maketh not in ſome ſort or other to ſerve Her turn, that each fancy may be ſatisfied, and each ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite find what to ſeed on. Whatſoever their Wealth can ſway with its Lovers; or voluntary Poverty with, the deſpiſers of the World; What Honour with the Ambitious; What Obedience with the Humble; What great Imployments with ſtirring or Martiall Spirits; as the Orders of Knights, that of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> thoſe now of <hi>Malta,</hi> that of the Kinghts of St. <hi>Morris,</hi> and St. <hi>Lazare</hi> amongſt the Savoyards, eſtabliſhed by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, 1644. the Knights of the Order of the Dogg and Cock in <hi>France:</hi> The firſt were to weare a Coller full of Staggs-Heads, with the Image of a Dogg to hang thereon, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie fidelity; theſe followed <hi>Philip</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>France</hi> in his Warrs: Thoſe of the Cock, ſignified watchfulneſſe, and had a Cock for their Blazon, for that the Antients accounted it to be a Bird of <hi>Mars;</hi> The Order of the Knights of the <hi>Ginit</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> The Order of the Knights of the <hi>Leli,</hi> in the Realm of <hi>Navarr;</hi> The Order of Knights of St. <hi>Mary</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of Sr. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Accon,</hi> and of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> of St. <hi>Saviour</hi> in <hi>Arragon,</hi> Knights of <hi>Mount-joy</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> King of <hi>Portingal,</hi> or men at Arms, St. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Spain:</hi> The Order of Knights of the Glorious Virgin in <hi>Italy;</hi> The Order of the Knights of the Golden fleece in the Houſes of <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Austria,</hi> with above 200 more Orders of Knights too large here to be mentioned. Theſe Orders are for their Metalld
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50653:4"/>and Active Spirits. Alſo, they have their perpetual proviſions, for their Heavy and Reſtive Bodies in their Cells; What content or pleaſure nature can take in Paſſe-times and Jollities; What contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-wiſe, the Auſtere mind in Diſcipline and Rigor; What Love, ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Chaſtity can Raiſe in the pure; or Voluptuouſneſs, in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure or diſſolute: What allurements, are in Knowledge to draw the Contemplative, or in Actions of State to imploy the Polititian: What Miracles with the Credulous: What Viſions with the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical: What Ceremonies can do with the Superſtitious: What Prayers with the Devout: What diſpenſing with breach of all Rules, with Men of lawleſſe condition: In ſum, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the heart of Man can deſire, he is fitted with, in the Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of the Church of <hi>Rome's</hi> Politicks; for himſelf to perſue, or at leaſt to Adore or Reverence in another. This is the main Wheel on which the Church moveth, and keepeth faſt, Members of all ſorts; ſo that, by this means of providing for the ſeveral Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of the Members, it enjoyeth the more quiet in it ſelf, and becometh able to oppoſe and diſturbe the Reformed Churches; They have two other ſtrings to their Bow; Beſides, this aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which is, indeed the chief. The firſt is their Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, is, their keeping the Laiety in Ignorance.</p>
            <p>For their miracles: the number are infinite, that they reckon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but they are all of the ſame Stamp and Impreſſion with theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> The repreſentation of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with the Babe, their Eyes to move at certain times: it is performed by Engine-work, ſecretly contrived to cheat the People into a belief of their Fopperies; the lifting up the hand of the Image of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, in imitation of Bleſſing the People: and the like. Her Image giving Milk on the Day of the Nativity, convayed by ſmall tinn-Pipes at a great diſtance, begot the admiration in the People, and an Implicit faith of all theſe wonders. A ſubtill Jeſuit ſhall make his abode five or ſix years more or leſſe, being blind (at leaſt ſeem ſo to be) by Dying the Inner skin of the Eye, by a water diſtilled from a certain Herb, not fit to be mentioned here; or ſeem Lame, or Leprozed; or otherwiſe by <hi>Guzmonds</hi> Art of raiſing an artificial Leproſie, now uſed among ſome Beggars, to move Compaſſion in the Charitable. When he is well known, he ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50653:5"/>come and implore the ayd of ſuch a Saint: Immediately he ſhall be as whole as a fiſh, and his ſight ſhall be reſtored; then that Saint is repaired unto far and nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; offerings come plentifully; Thus they contrive to enrich the Church, and if it chance that any Bath or Spring break forth of the Earth that paſſeth thorow any mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and is of Phyſical uſe (as all ſuch are) it is Dedicated to one Saint or other; and ſometimes waters, of no vertue at all Naturally, are cryed up to be for ſuch and ſuch uſes, as the Well or Water of Saint <hi>Winifrid,</hi> or the like precious Saint; People repair to it, to uſe it: the which, together with the opinion that they have of it, doth effect ſome kind of cures. It is a true ſaying, that the Patient's good opinion of the Phyſitian or means is more then half the cure. The Polititians of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> know the truth of that ſaying, therefore they uſe all means poſſible to increaſe the faith of their Patients or Clyents; which maketh their cure more certain and eaſie. That cure of the King's evil here in <hi>England,</hi> granted by the Pope, as a gift peculiar, to the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> had indeed no other vertue then what was extracted from the opinion of the Patient, created by the Majeſty of the King, the Solemnities and Circumſtances that attended the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the cure; therefore I allow that report to be true, that the blood of the Late King, ſaved upon an Handkercher, or other piece of linnen being dipt therein, hath cured that diſtemper of the King's Evil. It is known to Phyſitians, that ſeveral Diſtempers are cured by the ſtrength of Imagination, as well as ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſubjected to ſeveral Diſtempers by Imagination. As in time of Peſtilence; many that would dye of other Diſeaſes than what was prepared by the Humors, or Diſorders in nature. The Fear and Imagination of the Party diſtempered, is as a mould to caſt the form of the thing feared in: though others do dye of it, being prepared, as tinder is apt matter for fire; ſo they more aptly are ſubject to the Influences operating at that time. God maketh uſe of ſecond means, although that of the Plague be an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate diſpenſation from Him, and is as it were a thing diſtinct from, and other than, the ordinary workings of Nature.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are very well acquainted, and do much ſtudy Natural Magick, and are very good Proficients therein, as in many hundred caſes, they may be traced in their Legends; as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50653:5"/>moſt of all which, may be performed by the natural Magical Art, though they aſcribe unto them the honour of Miracles: As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> his great wonder of kindling a fire with Ice. We muſt here let you to know, that it is eaſie for Artiſts to make ſuch a compoſition, that ſo ſoon as one drop of water toucheth it, it ſhall become a violent flame; the which is effected by <hi>Antiperiſtaſis;</hi> that is to ſay, the ſtrengthning and oppoſing any quality againſt its contrary, as of cold againſt heat; it may be repreſented in a more familiar Example, as that of the firing of a Corn or Hay-Stacks, when Stackt too moyſt or wet; it doth not fire, becauſe of heat and dryth, but it fireth becauſe too moyſt or cold: which is able to oppoſe, though not overcome the other; qualities being ſtirred, devour the matter that retained them both. Alſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is acquainted with Sorcery, or Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Magick; the which, was practiſed by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6th. Who, the Papiſts themſelves cannot deny, but that he gave himſelf to the Devil; who was not onely the wickedeſt of Men, but alſo the wickedeſt of Pope's: He beſtowed the riches of the Church upon his Baſtards; he made away the Brother of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jazet</hi> for a ſum of money, though he fled to him for protection; he uſed his own Daughter <hi>Lucretia,</hi> the Wife to three Princes. Innumerable examples might be given of this nature, too large here to be inſiſted upon: So much, as to their Miracles, and the means by which they effect them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to their other Part or Branch of their policy, <hi>viz.</hi> Their practiſe to divide the reformed Churches: they do it by Inſtruments and Emiſſaries of their own, who are ſent to divide and infect them with Errors and Contradictions. They, out of the Seminaries, of the Order of Jeſu, do ſend uſually great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to all Parts to do this work. This Order was wholly Religious before <hi>Luther</hi>'s time, they vowed the preaching of the Goſpel to Pagans, and the Inſtructing Chriſtians in good Letters, <hi>gratis.</hi> When <hi>Luther</hi> began to oppoſe the Power of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they caſt off their Religious Vowes, and betook themſelves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Supremacy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be above general Councils and Princes, by principles and practiſes of policy, or rather Deviliſh circumventing cunning; for they Value not the way or means, by which they attain to the accompliſhing of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50653:6"/>what they undertake. When ſeeming Piety ſhall make way for what they deſign, they have it at their fingers Ends; when the moſt impious and wicked Act, that ever was on Earth done, muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh what they deſign they there alſo are moſt ready: But they make choice rather of ſeeming Sanctity, than of wicked Violations; becauſe the Church hath a better Salve to cure the wounds made by the former, than it hath for the wounds made by the latter.</p>
            <p>The manner of this political Order's Practiſe, you ſhall find in <hi>Campanella</hi>'s Diſcourſe, (one of that Order) touching the Spaniſh Monarchy, <hi>Chap.</hi> 25. He adviſeth the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the latter End of the Raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Now as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the weakning of the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>there can no better way poſſibly be found out, than by cauſing diviſion and diſſention amongſt them, and by continuall keeping up the ſame; which will quickly furniſh the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Crown, or the Church, with more opportunities and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges than the power of great Armies can procure or produce: As for the Religion of that People, it is that of</hi> Calvin, <hi>though very much moderated, and not ſo Rigid, and Auſtere as it is at</hi> Geneva; <hi>which yet cannot be ſo eaſily extinguiſhed or rooted out there, unleſſe there were ſome Certain Schools ſet up in</hi> Flanders; <hi>with which People, the</hi> Engliſh <hi>have great dealing and Commerce: by means of which there ſhould be ſcattered abroad the Seeds of Schiſm and Diviſion, in the natural Sciences; as namely betwixt the</hi> Stoicks, Peripateticks, <hi>and</hi> Teleſians <hi>by which the Errour of the</hi> Calviniſts <hi>might be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: For the Truth is, That Sect is diametrically contrary to the Rules of Policy; for they teach, that Whether a man do well or ill, he doth all by divine Impulſion; which</hi> Plato <hi>demonstrates againſt</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>to be oppoſite to all ſounder Policy, which ſaies, That every man hath free Liberty of Will, either to do well or ill; So that it is in our power to do and obſerve whatever is commanded, and from hence we are to expect our Reward or Puniſhment; according as I have taught in my Dialogue touching Policy, where I have diſcourſed of this poynt, though but briefly; which they, ſince they have become Hereticks, are grown ſomewhat ſubtill in; and yet being of a Nature that is ſtill deſirous of Novelties and Change, they are eaſily wrought over to any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here may be diſcerned what advantage they have over us in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Religion. I recited his whole Aphoriſm, as to that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50653:6"/>that the Reader may perceive the Order and Working of theſe Politicians; who lay their Deſigns deep: they ſtudy Men, their Minds, Objects, Cauſes, and their Effects, and the Effects of Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, <hi>ad Infinitum:</hi> They this day have lulled this Nation into ſo many ſeveral Lethargies and Sleeps; wherein, Thoſe of this perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dream, they only are in the truth, and all others in Errours; So thoſe of another, do the like of the former, and the like of others.</p>
            <p>And thus the Jeſuit hath divided us, by his obſerving the ſeveral Humours of the Engliſh Nation; As to the People that are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly given, there is the Epiſcopal; thoſe that are more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere, as the Presbyterian; thoſe that are more pure, as the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, or ſeperate Churches; the Anabaptiſts, as holy and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and as Perſons ſet a part from the World, by their Submiſſion to that Ordinance of Baptiſm, at years of Diſcretion: The Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is not much material, yet the Jeſuit maketh uſe of theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, to carry on his deſign, by promoting of every one of them, and by keeping them at an eeven poyſe; and ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſubdivide, that thereby, whilſt he divideth them that are moſt near to the Truth, he may work the better upon thoſe that are of a baſer Mind and Humor, and that will receive more groſs Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, more remote from the Truth: And thoſe he practiſeth upon ſuch who have not a ſpirit of diſcerning, but have ſome Affection to Devotion, as on the Seeker an the Quaker; more loſer Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples on the Familiſts and Ranters; merrier and pretty-conceited Devotions amongſt the Roſicrucians, and Pſalteriſts, or Haliluja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, or Singers; ſo of many others: I do not ſay, that the Jeſuit was the Creatour or Inſtitutor of the former, that is of the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, Presbyterian, or Independent; but he ſometimes muſt make uſe of Truth, and the waies of Truth, to gain advantages in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; as the Devils in the poſſeſſed, ſaid, <hi>What have we to do with thee,</hi> Jeſus <hi>of</hi> Nazareth; <hi>thou Son of the most High God?</hi> The Devil acknowledged Chriſt to be the Son of God, in deſign: for the People ſeeing him to be acknowledged by the Devils, they drew this Concluſion, that he did caſt out Devils by the Power of <hi>Belze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub</hi> the Prince of Devils: the Devils would never have confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that he was the Son of God, but to produce that contrary Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: So the Jeſuit doth not promote, or caſt himſelf under, thoſe forms that are true, or near the Truth, to any other end than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50653:7"/>thoſe contrary Effects, before premiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> to divide and ſubdivide, to render the Churches leſſe formidable or powerful in oppoſing the Church of Rome; if not ſubvert them, and bring them back to the Obedience of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> That this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and not taken up upon conjecture, is evident, by the practiſe of <hi>Thomas Ramſy,</hi> of the order of Jeſus, who joyned with a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Church at <hi>Hexam,</hi> in the North of <hi>England,</hi> under this pretence, hat he was a Jew, and gave himſelf this name, <hi>Joſeph Ben Iſrael;</hi> his particular Inſtructions was to inſinuate the Doctrine of Free-Will, the which he did accompliſh, and carryed on with a High hand, untill he was diſcovered, detected, and caſt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: One then in the ſame Priſon, the Gate-Houſe-<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that got more than ordinary advantages of Familiarity, obtained of him the Diſcovery of many rare ſecrets in the Policy of the Jeſuits practiſe, ſome of which are theſe; The waies that they practiſe in their Seminaries, to bring up youth, and temper them fit for the intended Imployments, they put them upon; They, Firſt obſerve the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Party, and obſerving the peculiar Gifts he is naturally indowed with, they fit him onely for that ſervice; he learneth ſome Trade (to hide and blind his Order,) which he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth; by this means he becometh Eminent amongſt of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion he caſteth himſelf into: and, to put him in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that he may be freed from the ſtings of Conſcience, they firſt teach him to ſwear, curſe, damn, and forſwear; and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to implore the Throne of Grace, with all pious Devotion imaginable: By this means they become flexible, and fit for any deſign that lyeth before them to promote; and if Conſcience ſtill ſhould purſue them, their pardons help at a deed lift.</p>
            <p>And this they warrant from that Maxim, That no way is to be refuſed, whereby the Felicity and Peace of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be promoted and ſecured: Let it be by any means whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, lawful or unlawful. Theſe things conſidered, How much doth it behove all that truly fear God, or have any true ſincere Religion in their breaſt, to deteſt and decline the thought of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning this forme, or that; in regard Religion doth not lye in forms, but in the powerful practiſe of all holineſſe, and godly Converſation; and therefore conſent to ſome Natural Harmony, or forme neceſſarie to the Truth for liberty of conſcience, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50653:7"/>the union thereof may be ſuch, as it may be able to make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s deſigns, and the Projects of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; elſe we ſhall continually be divided and ſubdivided, till at laſt we ſhall neither have form or ſubſtance left, and be hurried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all manner of Confuſion. The Truth of which is to be ſeen at this day amongſt us: How do the giddy &amp; unſtable run out of one form to another! The Devil and Jeſuit can ſcarcely invent that which hath either ſeeming Form or Order in it, faſt enough, or ſo faſt, as giddy People, that were never well principl'd in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are ready to be led away captive by poiſonous Notions that are daily diſtilled amongſt them, to the ruine of their own Souls, and to the diſhonour of God: Who, ſo ſoon as they are tainted by thoſe deluſions, immediately think themſelves illuminated by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light, as we ſee by ſad Experience at this day amongſt us, by People that yield obedience, and ſubmit to all manner of Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conform to them as Impulſes from on high; which is nothing elſe but the Effects of depraved minds agitated, illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and acted by the Evil One.</p>
            <p>The Truth of which was experimented upon one <hi>Hunt,</hi> who, in the year 1653, in <hi>January,</hi> being committed to the Gate-houſe Priſon, <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for his ſtrange Prophecies of the <hi>Stuart</hi>'s coming again to the Crown; that he was ſent of God, to perſwade old <hi>Cromwell</hi> to reſign his new-aſſumed Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Protector-ſhip. Some of the Priſoners there had a deſign to try whether they could not impoſe ſome Revelation upon this poor deluded Perſon, who pretended ſo much to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and Prophecy; (obſerve, that he was one of thoſe who, as the Apoſtle ſaith, are given over to believe Lye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>). At that time there were three Jeſuits, one of which was <hi>Ramſey</hi> aforementioned, who aided in the undertaking. The firſt par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t acted was to write a Letter in Hebrew, which was written by <hi>Ramſey,</hi> the Prophet <hi>Hunt</hi> being gone to bed before. The Keeper locks him up, the Keeper left the Letter upon a Table in the Room, being folded up in an unuſual form, with this Superſcription; <hi>To the Servant of the moſt high, PAUL HUNT:</hi> Next morning divers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners riſe juſt at the time of unlocking, and walk in the Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into which Prophet <hi>Hunt</hi>'s Chamber-door opened, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Excellent Muſick and ſinging they heard about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50653:8"/>the Clock that Morning, every one praiſed it above meaſure, and affirmed the Voyces to excell humane Voyces, and the Muſick to excell Humane Art, and alſo alleadged that it was about the Prophet's Lodging: they all ſpake loud enough, that he ſhould hear what they diſcourſed of. So after a little time, two or three entered the Prophet's Chamber, and recited what every one diſcourſed of: the Prophet, immediately ſaid, <hi>That he did hear Muſick, but he was caſt in a deep ſleep, and what the mind of God was in it, he knew not, but he ſhould wait his good pleaſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> So one of the Company caſting his eye upon the Table, eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Letter, askt the Prophet what Letter that was, folded up in ſo unuſual a form. Every one ſtood at a diſtance from the Table, to free him from ſuſpecting any of the Company, to bring it, or lay it there; The Prophet thereupon repaireth to the Table, and taketh it up, and readeth the Superſcription as aforementioned; he expreſſing extraordinary joy and gladneſſe, openeth it, and in it was written in the Hebrew. An Order of Church-Government, as alſo an Order of Civil-Government: withall, a Charge to him upon pain of the diſpleaſure of the moſt High, that he ſhould go or write to the then new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made Protector, and require him to ſurrender his Government to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> with many other things. Out of hand he demanded of the Keeper to open the Priſon, that he might go and deliver the Meſſage of the Lord to the then Uſurper <hi>O. C.</hi> Who refuſed to let him go. He conſulted with ſome of the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers what to do. One of them replyed that the Command did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly require him to go or ſend, which implyed, he might write; the which he did &amp; ſtuft three or four Sheets ſo full of Invectives, that had he ſent it to (but the Priſoners were ſo careful, that they prevented the delivery of the Letter) old <hi>Oliver,</hi> he would have hanged him without all peradventure. They fained an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and perſued the deſign much further to the admiration of many worthy Gentlemen, (State Priſoners there at that time), who ſaw in part what might be effected in things of that nature, upon the mindes of ſuch perſons that are given up to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50653:8"/>
            <p>The Art of the Jeſuits in this particular, is manifeſt. Another way which ſerveth them to great purpoſe, is, the looſening of People from principles; and when effected, diſtill Notions to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue after the diſcovery of new Lights, and inſtead of meeting with that which is Light, they cloſe with what ſuteth to their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Mindes or Ends: The Inferiour ſort of every perſwaſion, when the Jeſuit hath diſtilled his poyſon amongſt them, receive the Notions and Principles as Truth, and many of them worſhip under thoſe Forms and Notions, as in Spirit and Truth. The chief of moſt of them do Joyn with them out of corrupt Ends, to be Heads of the factions, to exerciſe a kind of Domination, which is delightful to mankind: ſo that the Jeſuite doth no more then firſt diſtilt Poyſonous Notions, and nurſe it, and defend it till it be indifferent conſiderable: when accompliſhed, it will ſubſiſt of it ſelf, and put it ſelf into Form and Order. Then when he hath done that by error, if that ſhould grow too faſt, he allayeth it by ſubdividing of it by ſome true Notion, or ſome other erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous notion, which are equally a like to the Jeſuit, for that the end of his deſign is, Dividing. When he hath devided and caſt a Nation into many and various Forms, he hath accompliſhed and arrived to his End; then, if he can Procure, Forment, or Stirr up Diſſatisfaction and Jealouſies betwixt the Intereſts, there he keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them in continual ebbing &amp; flowing; and naturally every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion will incline ſome to one Intereſt of State, ſome to another: As for example, the Epiſcopal doth naturally encline to a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, the Presbytery doth alſo encline to a Monarchy, but that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall; for the Presbytery is well ſuited, as to its form, for a Commonwealth; but here, when it ſtarted from the Intereſt of the Common-wealth, it was neceſſitated, becauſe it was ſuſpected by the then Supream Power, therefore it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heared to the Intereſt of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and eſpouſed his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. The Independent, naturally incline to a Commonwealth. The fifth Monarchy to an Oligarchy; that is to ſay, a Select com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Men to Govern, ſo and ſo qualified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Campanella</hi> did give the King of <hi>Spain</hi> the beſt advice to practiſe this kind of policy; yea, he commendeth it before the oppoſing of <hi>England</hi> by Arms. The reaſon why he choſe the Doctrine of free will to be firſt ſet on foot in <hi>England,</hi> was, becauſe that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50653:9"/>opinion concludeth Man to be a free Agent, which looſeneth and freeth the diſciples thereof from more firm and ſounder Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and prepareth them to ſeek after new Lights; and when once arrived to this degree, immediately they turn <hi>Enthuſiasts,</hi> who pretend, or think that all they do, is done by the Spirit, and that they are attended by the ſpirit of Revelation: Our Quaker is much peſtered with the Malignant Influence of this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuit by this means doth not onely divide People, as to Religion, and thereby render them leſſe formidable againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo bringeth an evil Report upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion; diſuniteth the affections of the profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and cauſeth Jealouſies, Heart-burnings, and Animoſities, one againſt the other; and taketh them off from the Power of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to defend paultry forms and diſtinctions: and, that which is worſt of all, thereby increaſeth ſo many diſtinct and different Intereſts of State, as there are conſiderable perſwaſions in a Commonwealth that Cheriſheth Religion, as is in part ſhewed before. When a perſwaſion is grown up to be conſiderable, it giveth occaſion for factions in State; Thereby, ſome ambitious men will become the Heads of this or that faction, and by the Power of the faction they head, become Mighty, and ſometimes arive to the top of Supreamacy thereby.</p>
            <p>But of all Perſwaſions, Opinions, or notions, that of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſt is the moſt dangerous and inconvenient to a Common-wealth; for when that the Jeſuit hath infuſed that Opinion, (That, what ever is given into their hearts after praying or ſeeking to God, muſt needs be the mind of God, and purſued with all vigour and earneſtneſſe to the death,) they then do nothing but roul out of one Change into another; and out of one thing into another; and a State or Power having gotten once out from the Center or Baſis of true Intereſt, by ſuch wicked prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, they ſhall never return nor take Sanctuary at Settlement and Safety; before utter ruine and deſtruction: as is plainly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in theſe few Lines following that is to ſay; A State or Power having once repaired to extraordinary means, to accompliſh this or that Deſign; if they have ſucceſſe in it, immediately they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude God hath done it for them; and ſo repaire to one extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50653:9"/>Undertaking after another, ſo often as they have opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conclude into be righteous, ſo often as they have ſucceſſe: which may as well and juſtly be concluded by him that robbeth or killeth on the High way if he were in a Capacity ſtrong enough to protect himſelf from Juſtice, he would ſeem righteous; and, in ſtead of being Hanged by the Judge, he would execute the Judge. The Error that ſuch People, States, or Powers, are in, is, that they were Principles and Rules, and Act neither by Principles nor Rules: but prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und to themſelves the Object or End; that is no ſay; what they would have or deſire; then they ſeek God; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards conſult; and if by conſultation it be found attainable, then it is the mind of God; if not, the contrary. God is to be ſought in all undertakings; nay, it is an underlable Duty: but, in ſeeking Him; reſpect is to be had to the Juſtice of what we ſeek for: Now, in this. Man is very ſubject to be led out of the way of Truth, for, he is very apt to conclude that what he would have, is juſt: the deſire or affection is paſſion, and paſſion doth Cloud the Judgment; and that which is true in one holdeth proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably true in more then one, being united by one Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <p>Now, if the Judgment be ſo Clouded by private affection, and a State or Power be led by ſuch Principles; What wickedneſſe ſhall not they be led into? What villanies ſhall not they attempt? What ſo ſacred, that they ſhall not violate? Or, what Intereſt or Right will not they invade? What ſhall limit them, if they find opportunity to attempt the accompliſhing or the attaining to their deſire? Miſerable is that Nation that hath ſuch a Prince or Power, Civil, or Military; that are poyſoned with ſuch Opinions: ſuch Powers, are ridd by the Jeſuit: who, will ride them, not onely out of breath, but at laſt to death: The World is miſtaken, when they apprehend that the Jeſuit worketh immediately in Councels to produce Turns and Changes of State; No, but he worketh by remote Cauſes, ſuch as are here before premiſed; than is to ſay, by infuſing Notions deſtructive to publick ſafety, at firſt into the common People, then it is drunk in by great Ones, then it Cleaveth and Divideth a Nation into ſo many Intereſts as there are, Perſwaſions; then he applyeth matter ſutable to the Humor, and moſt apt to be received by the ſeveral perſwaſions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50653:10"/>which ſhall work naturally ſuch Effects; and as it is the policy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to preſerve it ſelf, by providing ſutable enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment for each Humor within it ſelf; ſo, it is to deſtroy other Churches, by ſeveral poyſons for each Humor.</p>
            <p>Therefore it behoveth all Chriſtian States to endeavour to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie themſelves with a conſiſtence. Thoſe that cannot attain to a conſiſtency (<hi>England</hi> is much to be feared that it cannot arive to that happineſſe,) are in a miſerable condition: When a State hath arrived to conſiſtency, its Form and Order, is a barr to the Jeſuits operations. Thoſe States that are divided have no means to ſtay themſelves from falling down the precipice of inevitable ruine, but to ſettle the form of Government amongſt them, with reſpect to all Intereſts as Men. The excluſion of any Intereſt is dangerous. For their different Intereſts as Chriſtians, the Supream Magiſtracy ought to be an equal A bitrator, and ought to protect them equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; But here, care is to be had, that the Supream Power (if in a Commonwealth) be not lodg'd in one Intereſt. If it be, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that Intereſt do permitt freedom of exerciſe to different perſwaſions, by that liberty of conſcience cannot be long preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; for if the Supream Power be lodg'd in one Intereſt, it naturally will fortifie if ſelf by ſuch reaſons of State, that it will ſever it ſelf from the Intereſt of the Publick. Therefore, Liberty of conſcience to the ſeveral perſwaſions muſt be preſerved by divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or diſtributing the Power equally; elſe thoſe that are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded will become Enemies to that which is intruſted with, or aſſumeth, the Power: and thoſe which have it, ſhall never hold it with ſecurity or Peace, for the Jeſuit will ſtill he practiſing by his remote applications, to divide and widen the different Intereſts or perſwaſions, that the product will be nothing leſſe; or elſe, then Joſling one another out of Power, and the weakeſt will alwayes adhear or apply themſelves, to that where it can expect Sanctuary and Protection. That this general Rule, and all other good Means muſt be uſed to prevent the workings of the Jeſuit, is of abſolute neceſſity. The different Perſwaſions and Intereſts, are to unite, to prevent them of matter, to work upon an unſettled and divided Commonwealth, ought to be ſettled at once upon ſuch principles and Baſis, that there may be ſufficient proviſion for all things, to the ſatisfaction of all Intereſts, that none of them ſhould have place
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50653:10"/>left to deſire any other conſtitution: If the Founders of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth cannot hitt that mark, their undertaking herein will be obortive, and the Commonwealth ſhall do nothing but reel from one uncertainty to another. The Jeſuit doth not onely operate by diſtilling Notions in Religion, but alſo in affairs of State; as for Example, in the Caſe of our Controverſies with the Late King: The King, He Offendeth the People; the Parliament thereupon make Warr with Him, becauſe they ſee that the diſcontents of the People will bear them out, and inable them ſo to do; the which diſcontents were, no doubt, heightned very much by the Jeſuit. When the Warr was Ended, the King being beheaded, the Jeſuit alſo did practiſe and endeavour to incline the People to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: but in its Infancy alſo he endeavoured to ſtifle it, and prevent its ariving to a conſiſtency, leſt it ſhould be too firm and heavy for him to move: for a Commonwealth that hath Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or annual Election, the Jeſuit is at a loſſe to practiſe upon, for that at every Change of Perſons in Government, he is to ſeek how to faſten his Correſpondency, and other advantages to carry-on his deſignes with. Alſo it is his deſigne to endeavour the altering of a Commonwealth again into a Monarchy, and a Monarchy that is erected out of a Commonwealth into an Oligarchy; not that any one of the forms of Government will be more Subſervient to his deſigne than other, but that he may alwayes practiſe Changes: by which means a Proteſtant State is exerciſed with ſtrugling Intereſts within it ſelf, ſo that it ſhall be leſſe formidable and dangerous to the Catholike States.</p>
            <p>That theſe things are not conjectures or taken up by ſuppoſition onely, or that theſe and ſuch other Rules and Practiſes they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, is plainly demonſtrable by <hi>Adam Contzen</hi> the Jeſuit, in his Politicks, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.17, 18.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Is to ſhew that Princes muſt determine of nothing in Religion, as having power to defend that which the Pope determineth of, but no power to appoint or change any thing themſelves, or judge of Controverſies. The Church muſt Judge and the Prince muſt Execute.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50653:11"/>
               <p>Take notice that one of their Maxims is, that the Magiſtrate hath nothing to do with matters of Religion. As that Maxim fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth their purpoſe to ſtrengthen the Power of the Church, and weaken that of the Magiſtrate in Catholike-States: So it ſerveth their purpoſe in Proteſtant States to weaken the Magiſtrate, and lay all in confuſion in the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Is to ſhew, That to preſerve Religion, (that is Popery), no other Religion ſhould be permitted: and that Riches tend much to ſtrengthen the Clergy, and preſerve Religion: And <hi>the poverty of the Protestant Miniſters</hi> (which muſt be by all means endeavoured).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As he here preſcribeth means to inrich the Popiſh Miniſtery, he adviſeth the impoveriſhing the Proteſtant, that they may become diſabled and diſcouraged to ſtudy and labour in the work of the Miniſtery, as alſo that by poverty they may become contemptible: Indeed the Proteſtant-Miniſter is the Eye-ſore to the Catholike, and thoſe that Cry out againſt Miniſters maintainance do nothing elſe then the work of the Jeſuit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">To bring in popery, and aboliſh, the Proteſtants Religion, is, to make uſe of the Proteſtants Contentions. How eaſie is it <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to bring the Puritans into Order, if they be forced to approve of Biſhops? or to reduce the Puritans in the Low Countries, if the Prince adhere to the <hi>Armiulans?</hi> For the Variety of Opinions makes that doubtful, that before ſeemed certain; ſo that when the Magiſtrate joyneth with one ſide, he eaſily overturns the other, and leaves the whole obnoxious: As <hi>Paul</hi> did by the diſſenſion between the Phariſees &amp; Sadduces, joyning to one ſide, he eſcaped. This <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> I would prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally perſwade an Orthodox Magiſtrate to <hi>(that is, a Papist.)</hi> For he may with as much advantage make uſe of the Proteſtants diſagreements as of the Papiſts Concord to extirpate Proteſtants. As in Warrs, it is not onely the skill and ſtrength of the General,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50653:11"/>but often alſo the Careleſneſſe of the Enemy, or his Miſtake that give very great advantages for ſucceſſe. When rigid <hi>Calvinſm</hi> was aſſaulted by the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in the heat of the Paroxyſm, it was exaſperated, and the ſodain reſtraint did much hurt: But now the <hi>Arminians</hi> have of their own accord let go the hardeſt part of their rigor, and judge the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> to be impious, and perſecute them in the very Univerſity, and in other Towns they force them to baniſhment; and would venture to do more and Crueller things, if they were not afraid of the ſtrength of the adverſe Party.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he here ſayth of Contentions, is ſufficiently practiſed: Firſt, To Create them; And Secondly, To Foment them. That which <hi>Contzen</hi> principally taketh notice of, is, that Order in the Puritans or Profeſſors of Religion in <hi>England,</hi> is eaſe to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: But he adviſeth that the Magiſtrate, or Agent for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do make uſe of the Proteſtants differences.</p>
               <p>The Major part of the Profeſſors of Religion, are ſenſible of the practiſes and agitations of the Jeſuits. The effects thereof that are produced daylie, are viſible. The chief power of a Nation ought to erect a private Council, whoſe only work ſhould be to gain Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, to obſerve their Seminaries and Colledges, to put in practiſe ſuch Rules of policy as may undermine their deſignes, and countermine their practiſes. How, and which way ſuch a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble work may be carryed on effectually, I ſhall here omitt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that it is not fit to be Publiſhed: The publiſhing thereof would do diſ-ſervice to the Proteſtant-Intereſt, in regard that what is fore-known may be eaſily prevented. Therefore, it ſhall be kept in ſilence untill God ſhall raiſe a Magiſtracy, whoſe heart ſhall be free to ſo noble a work as this will be; by which Chriſtians as Chriſtians, and Men as Men, will receive no ſmall Benefit: A State in general, and every Member in particular ſhall have cauſe to bleſſe God, for ſuch who ſhall promote this good work. No doubt but that it will be acceptable in the ſight of God: and they ſhall have the Prayers and the Praiſe of Men, the good of Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will be better ſecured as the caſe ſtandeth. Now, neither the Church or People of God nor the Nation, can be aſſured of any Stable or Conſtant condition, in regard we are ſo Rolled and Tumbled out of one uncertainty into another.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50653:12"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>The Jeſuit's Method to win particular Perſons. Reader, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them; for when thou findeſt theſe Rules practiſed; It is by a Jeſuit himſelf, or by one that hath bin his Pupil.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Be ſure to keep the Reſpondents part, and not the Opponents. It's not ſo eaſie to prove, as to wrangle againſt Proofs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Follow them with certain Queſtions, which the Vulgar are not verſt in. As</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Where was your Church before</hi> Luther? <hi>Or, Where hath it bin Viſible in all Ages?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 2. <hi>How prove you, that you have a true-Scripture that is the Word of God among you?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 3. <hi>What expreſſe Word of God do the Catholicks (the Papiſts) contradict?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 4. <hi>How prove you that you have a truly called Miniſtery, that is to be heard and believed by the People?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 5. <hi>By what warrant did you ſeparate from the Catholick Church, and condemn all your own Forefathers, and all the Christian World?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 6. <hi>If you will ſeparate from the Catholike Church, what reaſon have you to follow this Sect, rather than any one of all the rest?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 7. <hi>What one man can you name from the beginning, that was in all things of</hi> Luthers <hi>or</hi> Calvins <hi>Opinions?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Q. 8. <hi>Do you not ſee that God doth not bleſſe the Labours of your Miniſters, but People are as bad as they were before? What the better are you for hearing them?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Reader, Juſt upon the Cloſe, I met with this Paſſage in <hi>Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella, Chap.</hi> XVIII.</p>
            <p>Neither would I have this one thing to be omitted; namely, that He erect certain Colledges through all the Provinces of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50653:12"/>Dominions, in which ſhould be placed all the moſt Ingenious Boyes of the ſaid Provinces; (and who are ſuch, may eaſily be known, by their firſt Maſters, that taught them their Grammers, and other the Firſt Rudiments) and theſe, being thus culled out of all Grammer-Schools, I would have to be brought up, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at the Kings Charge; and there ſhould be a <hi>New Order</hi> ſet up of them, like that of St. <hi>Dominick;</hi> which <hi>Order</hi> I would have called, The <hi>Auſtrian Order.</hi> And when any of theſe were come to be 18 years old, they ſhould then be commanded to Preach: and theſe I would have to be called, <hi>The Kings Preachers;</hi> and they ſhould then be ſent abroad, ſome into <hi>Germany,</hi> and others into <hi>England:</hi> where, if they have managed their buſineſſe rightly, and well; at their return they ſhould have Biſhop-ricks conferred upon them by the King, of thoſe that are in the Kings own gift: for, by ſo doing, he ſhall render himſelf ſecure both from the pope, and alſo againſt all perfidious Preachers and Hereticks; and by this means ſuch perſons only ſhall be maintained at His Charge, as do him ſervice for it, and advance His affairs.</p>
            <p>He adviſeth a new Order, the which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> did. They were to be ſent into Proteſtants States to practiſe Diviſion, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Intereſt of the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> as the Jeſuit doth in behalf of the Churches Intereſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
